Hello.
Thank you for joining
CS 25 Transformers.
Today's the last class.
Today, we have Loubna, who is
a machine learning engineer
in the science team
at Hugging Face,
working on large language models
for code and synthetic data
generation.
She is part of the core
team at the BigCode project
and has co-authored the Stack
dataset and the StarCoder models
for code generation.
Thank you so much for
coming to our talk today.
And as always, the attendance
link and the Slido questions
are on our website and we'll be
taking questions after the talk.
Thank you, and you
can take it off now.
Hi.
Thank you for the introduction.
So I'm Loubna.
I'm a machine learning engineer
at Hugging Face in the science
team and today, I'll
tell you about the
behind the scenes for training
large language models.
And I will use the
StarCoder model
that our team has
trained as a use case.
So today's plan is very simple.
We're going to try to
answer this question.
What does it take
to train a good LLM?
So it's one question,
but it's very loaded
and it has a lot of follow
ups. And as you will see,
my slides will be a series
of questions and answers.
So a few years ago,
a lot of people
thought that there was
some molten secret sauce
to the song closed
models like GPT-4
and that it will take the open
source community a lot of time
to catch up because the open
source models that we had back
then were much smaller
and less performance.
But now, it seems that
the community figured out
most of the pieces for getting
strong LLMs as it was predicted
in this Google memo that
was leaked and released
on semi analysis.
For example, today we
have Llama 370b instruct,
which has almost the same
performance as GPT-4 but it
unlocked so many use cases
because the model weights are
open, the model can be quantized
and can even run on a consumer
desktop.
It also allows the community to
build very cool use cases on top
through fine tuning.
So we've made a lot of
progress in the open field
and this is not the only
model that's out there.
We're now observing a rise
of open LLMs in the company.
More and more companies are
embracing releasing models.
That was the case, for example,
with DeepMind's Gemma models
and with Mistral's models
and also other models
from GPT [INAUDIBLE].
Here, I put a plot
from the LMSYS Arena,
which is the go to
leaderboard for comparing
abstract models nowadays.
It uses human evaluation.
And you can see in this plot
that as we went from 2023 to May
24, the gap in performance
between the closed models
and the open models is
shrinking and becoming smaller,
which is very promising.
So we're on a very great
path but there are still
a lot of limitations for this.
And this is mainly due
to releases missing out
important details about
how the data was processed
and how the models were trained.
And this is usually the
case for two main reasons.
The first one is to
avoid legal scrutiny,
because when companies
publicly disclose the training
data, if the training
was not done properly
and the copyrighted
were not respected,
they risk facing
legal investigation.
The other reason for not
disclosing the details
can be to maintain
a competitive edge.
So some companies want to
be the best at training LLMs
so they don't want to give all
the details for their training.
Nevertheless, because we
have a lot of releases,
I think we can still answer this
question and put a lot of pieces
together.
So what do we need
to train a good LLM.
The first thing is
probably the model.
You need to have a
good architecture.
And I think now,
transformers are the default,
but there are also other
interesting architectures
like Mamba, which is
a state space model,
or you can use mixture
of experts, which can
be multiple transformer models.
But I'm not going to
spend a lot of time
in this lecture on
models because I think
it's a topic that's
already thoroughly explored
and there are other aspects
that maybe deserve a little bit
more attention.
So that was it for models.
Then for GPUs, I
don't think there's
much I can tell you about that,
except maybe I ask Jensen.
But the part that they
were the most interested of
is the data, which I think
is the backbone of LLMs
because now, almost
everyone is using
the same architecture and
the same training techniques.
And for a given budget, data is
what makes some models better
than the others.
So it's really worth spending
time exploring this data
and understanding how to
get higher quality samples.
So now, we're going to try to
answer our previous question
of how to train a good LLM by
how do we get good training
data?
And I think the answer
to this is threefold.
First, we need to understand
how much data do we need?
And then once we figured
out the size of the data
that we need, where can we
get this data and to clean it,
which filtering
techniques make more sense
and will give us the
best performance.
So to answer the first
one, the answer to that
is the scaling laws.
You want to know which
data, how much data you
want to train your model
on, but also what is
the optimal size of the model.
And the scaling
laws try to study
the allocation of a
compute budget between data
size and model size.
This means should you
take a smaller model
and train it longer
or take a larger model
and train it on less data.
And I'm going to present a brief
history of the scaling laws
because I think it's really
interesting to see how
the sizes of the models
progress through time and also
how the size of the data sets
and the number of tokens we
train on them have changed
because there were really
some drastic changes in that.
I think the first to
establish the scaling
laws were Kaplan from OpenAI.
And they tried to fit the
law as a function of--
the laws as a function of
the data size and model size.
And they found that
if you have a 10 times
increase in your compute, you
should increase your parameter
count by 5.5, but
your training tokens,
you should only
increase them by 1.8.
This means that if you have more
resources to train your models,
you should make the model much
larger but the data is fine.
You shouldn't
increase it that much.
And this is what led to
models like GPT-3, which
is 175 billion
parameters, but it
was only trained on $300 billion
tokens, which, if we think
about it now, is really small.
Other models also followed
this, for example,
like OPT, which was
the same size as GPT-3
and trained on a
similar amount of data.
There was also BLOOM.
So all these models are
actually very under trained.
Then the Chinchilla
scaling laws came after
and they revisited
the scaling laws.
And they found that
the reason Kaplan
thought that data
should not be as scaled
as model size is because they
used a fixed cosine scheduler
for all their experiments.
So although they were
changing the data size,
the cosine scheduler was fixed.
This meant that for
some models, they
were underestimated
because they were not
using the correct cosine that
corresponded to the data size.
This led to false conclusions
and the Chinchilla
can now give us new
scaling laws that
say that you should
scale your data
and your model size equally.
And in their paper,
they train a 65 billion
model on 1.6 trillion tokens,
which is the Chinchilla optimal
point.
And they outperform much larger
models like GPT-3 and Gopher,
which was over 200
billion parameters.
So here, for example,
I have a plot
which shows what the
scaling laws try to do.
For example, here you
have IsoFLOP curves, which
each curve uses a fixed budget.
And then you try to find
the sweet spot, which
is the optimal for
your budget allocation
and it tells you what
your model size should be
and what your data
size should be.
And as you can see here,
if we try to fit the loss,
we can see that there's a linear
increase for data and also model
size.
In this scheme, I
tried to show how
we've moved from the Chinchilla
scaling laws to today's models.
And you can see that, for
example, the Chinchilla model,
which is 60 billion
parameters, was trained
on less than 2 trillion tokens.
But then after
that, we have Llama,
which was released last year,
and it was just a 7B model
and it was trained on as much
data as the Chinchilla model.
So it was trained way past
the Chinchilla optimal point.
And we might be wondering,
why is that the case?
Did Meta not use their compute
budgets in an optimal way?
And the answer to that is that
compute optimal is not always
optimal because when
you train a model,
you don't only care
about what you're
going to spend in training, but
you also care about inference.
And the model is
trained one time
but inference is for more the
model is going to be served.
So you want to save
some cost in that.
This makes it that people prefer
training smaller models longer
than actually using
much larger models that
are trained on less data.
So this was the
case for Llama 1,
for other models like
Mistral, but also for Llama 3
which went even further and
trained not on 1 trillion tokens
but on 15 trillion tokens.
And if you check
the archive paper,
the loss kept going down and
also the downstream evaluations
as the model training
is kept improving.
I think this is
really interesting
because some people
misunderstood the Chinchilla
scaling laws as compute
optimal, optimal
but that's not the case because
the inference cost is not
considered.
So for example, this is the
cost for training GPT-4.
It is said that it's estimated
that $100 million, but also
the inference is very
expensive and the larger
the model becomes, the more
time it takes to process tokens.
So inference, the scaling laws
don't take the inference costs
into consideration.
And if we do take the
inference cost, which
is the case for most
people because they want
to use these models
in inference,
you might prefer using smaller
models and training them longer.
And we do that, we're not
respecting the Chinchilla
scaling laws, so we're
choosing to pay what
we call a compute overhead.
It's a sacrifice that you
do during the training.
You choose to pay more, but
this will have a benefit
during inference
because you will
save a lot of cost and money.
And there's this very
interesting blog post
about Hartman's law, which tries
to measure the compute overhead
that you will be paying when you
choose to train a small model.
For example, here, there's
the space on Hugging
Face where you can
input the model size
and what data sets
you want to train on,
and it will show you where you
are regarding the Chinchilla
optimal point.
So, for example, if we take
7B model and we train it on 1
billion tokens, you can
see that we are here.
It's the red dots and it's
before the Chinchilla optimal
model.
And this gives approximately,
I think, a 40% overhead.
But then during inference, as
it shows here in the table--
sorry, it was 13% overhead, but
there's almost 50% saving costs.
So that's something that's
almost everyone is doing now,
which is why we see models
that are much, much smaller
than one or two years ago.
For further reading, there are
some very interesting papers
about scaling laws.
For example, this paper called
Scaling Data-Constrained
Language Models, which shows
that if you are limited
in your data size,
let's say, for example,
you wanted to finish 7B on
10 trillion tokens but you
don't have these
10 trillion tokens,
this paper says that you can
basically repeat your data up
to four times, so four epochs,
and you will get similar
performance as if you
use the unique tokens.
So for example, instead of
using a trillion tokens unique,
you could use just 2 and
repeat them four times
and you get almost
the same performance
as if these tokens were unique.
And this is especially
useful for some domains
where we almost exhaust all the
data that's publicly available.
As I will show you later,
the Stack v2, which
is a code data set
that we released,
I think it has almost all the
code that is available publicly
so it's going to be very hard
to scrape and get more code.
And if you want to
train models longer,
the only option is to actually
repeat the data during training.
And this is good news
because repeating the data up
to four times is
actually significant.
Another paper that I
think is interesting
when it comes to scaling
laws is the DeepSeek LLM.
They try to establish
new scaling laws that
are suited for the data because
they found that the scaling
behavior is highly dependent
on the data quality.
So they tried different data
subsets, different filterings,
and they found that the
scaling laws were changing.
So this is very important
because up until now,
we were using the Chinchilla,
but the Chinchilla
was using fixed data sets.
They are not necessarily the
ones that we are using now,
so it's really important
to be aware of that.
And this is why DeepSeek
tried to come up
with their own scaling laws
that work for their data sets.
And they also conclude that
when you have higher quality
data sets, maybe more compute
should be allocated to the model
size and not to the data size.
So these are interesting
things to keep in mind
when it comes to scaling LLMs.
So we have answered the
first question, I hope,
how much data to train LLMs.
So let's say now you have
your compute budget, a fixed
number of GPUs for a
certain amount of days,
and you also know approximately
how much data you want to use.
The question is that, where
do you find this type of data?
For example, Llama 3 was
trained on 15 trillion tokens,
but where do you get
15 trillion tokens?
That's a huge number.
To get this data,
the two main sources
where you can actually get
very large volume of data
are the web and
then GitHub code.
There are some other curated
sources that are of high quality
but are much smaller, like
Wikipedia books, archive,
or StackExchange.
You can also get
data, a new type
that's been very
trendy recently,
which is synthetic data.
But let's first start
with the sources where
you can get very large volumes.
The first one is web data.
So that's basically web pages.
And usually, people
to create these data
sets, they start
from CommonCrawl,
which is a public repository
of crawled web pages.
CommonCrawl crawls
pages regularly
and they publish dumps
every few months.
But if you start
from there, you will
need to do some heavy filtering
at a very large scale.
For example, just the latest
dump has over 400 terabytes,
and they have almost 95 dumps.
So that's not a very
easy task, and you
will need to have a lot
of resources and a team
to be able to do that crawling.
The other option is to use
an existing filtered web
data set where researchers
already filtered the CommonCrawl
and released them.
And luckily, we
do have data sets
that are very large
and well filtered.
One of them is the web data
FineWeb, that was recently
released by Hugging
Face, and it has
15 trillion tokens of web data.
It's not just a large
data set, but it also
has the best performance among
the publicly available data
sets.
And here, for example,
it shows the performance,
which is an aggregation over
multiple popular benchmarks
for NLP like HellaSwag,
MMLU, and others.
And it's averages them and
compares to other data sets
like C4, RefinedWeb,
SlimPajama, and The Pile.
So that was for web.
So you can get 15
trillion tokens easily.
And then for code data, we
have released the stack data
set, which is the largest
data set of open source code.
This data set comes
in two versions.
Version one consisted of six
terabytes of permissive code.
And how we build
this data set is
that we first cloned all the
public repositories on GitHub.
So this gave us over
130 repositories
and 100 terabytes of data.
But we don't want all of
that data because a lot of it
can be configs or extensions
that we don't need
or languages that are
no longer maintained.
So we did some file
extension filtering
and we ended up with almost
90 terabytes of data.
After that, we
filtered repositories
based on their licenses so we
can have permissive licenses
like Apache 2 or MIT.
You can have more restrictive
licenses like GPL.
So we filtered all the
repositories that did not
have a permissive license.
And after that, we
did a deduplication
to remove files
that are similar.
So we ended up with almost 3
terabytes of deduplicated data.
The stack comes also with a
very cool tool for opt out.
This tool is basically a
space where you can go.
You can type your
GitHub username
and it tells you if you have
any of your GitHub repositories
in the data set.
And if that's the
case, there's also
an option to fill
a form and request
to be removed from all the
future trainings of BigCode.
So we did that for the second
one, but also for the stack v2.
In the v2 is a much
larger and enhanced
data set compared to the v1.
This time, instead of
cloning GitHub repositories,
we went through
Software Heritage,
which is an archive of code.
They already did the scraping
and we just extracted the data
from their archive.
And we ended up, after
all the filtering,
with almost 1
trillion tokens, which
is a lot compared to the
v1 where we got around 200
billion tokens at the end.
We also added some high quality
resources like GitHub issues,
math and coding data
sets, and pull requests.
So these data sets, the
stack v1, the stack v2
can be used to train LLMs on
code or to train general LLMs
and include code as a subset
of the general web data.
This shows how the stack
v2 compares to the v1.
And you can see that
before filtering, it's
almost 10 times larger
and after filtering, it's
four or five times larger.
So I talk about how to get web
data, how to get code data,
and then I also
mentioned synthetic data.
And it's this year and last year
that synthetic data became very
important for LLM training.
And I think that in
the next few years,
it will become even
more important.
And I think this was
mainly sparked by the five
series of models by Microsoft.
The first paper was called
textbooks are all you need.
And they basically generated
synthetic textbooks using
GPT-3.5 and GPT-4, and
they tried to build a new
pre-training corpus that is
synthetic and they were able
to match and outperform models
that are trained on web data
sets.
So this model was trained on
almost entirely synthetic data.
But now, some of the
very popular LLMs
are using synthetic data as
part of their pre-training mix.
For example, Claude
3, in the model car,
they say that they
generate data internally
and they include it
in the pre-training.
This is also the
case for Llama 3,
where they use the LLMs
to build classifiers
that would annotate samples and
only keep the high quality ones.
But they also generated
synthetic content
to improve performance on coding
and reasoning and long contexts.
So synthetic data
is a very new topic,
but it seems really interesting.
I'm personally working also
on that as Hugging Face.
We recently released a data
set called Cosmopedia, which
was the largest data
set of synthetic texts,
and it had almost
25 billion tokens.
And instead of using
closed models like GPT-4,
it used an open source
model, which is Mixtral-8x7B.
And we also released
a blog post that
explains how we
created this data set
because it can be very tricky
to get very diverse samples.
So we used an
approach where we had
80% of the data that
comes from the web,
and then we try to use
these web samples to build
new prompts that ask models
to generate text books that
are related to
these web samples,
but while giving
them more context
so we can limit the generations.
For example, we can have a
topic that is a mathematics,
and then we have web samples
that are related to mathematics.
And each time we give the
model a prompt, generate
a textbook in the field
of mathematics that
is related to this web sample.
And the more web samples we
add, the more diversity we add.
We also use some curated
sources like Stanford courses
and wikiHow, where we use
extracts from these pages
to ask the models to generate
content that is related to them.
You can find more details
in the Cosmopedia blog post.
So I guess now, we
also have the answer
for our second question, which
was where to find the data.
And if you're following,
we have one question left,
which is, how can
we filter this data?
Because for example, if you
use CommonCrawl and you need
to filter it, and even
if you use the stack,
we did not train our models
on the stack directly.
We did a lot of filtering to
get a data set that is smaller
but has a higher quality.
And for this data set,
I will cite this slide
from Thomas Wolfe's
presentation.
This lecture is very
interesting, by the way.
You can find it here.
And this is from
the Yi paper, where
they state that a
high quality data
set might exhibit very
advanced capabilities
for a standard architecture.
And this is actually the
focus of many recent papers
and we can see that
in model releases,
the sections about data sets
are becoming smaller and smaller
because people are realizing
that the data set is actually
the backbone.
It is the one that is making
some models much better
than others.
So it's really
important to spend
a lot of time curating
these data sets
and trying to remove all
the outliers and data
sets that can hurt the
model during the training.
This is the pipeline from
the Yi paper for filtering
their crawled web data sets.
So first, they do
language filtering.
So I guess in Yi's
case, they kept English
and some Asian languages.
Then they apply some
filtering techniques
to remove low quality samples.
For example, there
are some metrics,
you look for files that
have a lot of lines repeated
and then you remove them.
There's also
rule-based collection.
You also can use
perplexity filtering
where you compute
something like loss
and remove samples that
have a very high one.
Then after that,
they also did a step
which is very important,
deduplication,
because there are a
lot of papers that
study the effect of
duplicates on training
and they find that skipping
duplicates in the training data
can cause models to memorize
and they have less space
to be creative.
So this hurts the
performance of models
and it's always advise
to remove duplicates.
Using exact
duplication, to remove
files that are exactly
identical, but also
near deduplication to remove
files that are similar.
And this uses techniques
like MinHash deduplication.
For Yi, after that, they also
did more filtering on top
like semantic and
topic filtering.
But usually, you can do
the classic filtering
and duplication and then be more
creative for the other filters.
This was also the
case for FineWeb.
The reason it is better
than other data sets is
that because they spent
a lot of time trying
to come up with better filters
and also deduplicate the data
sets well.
Now the question is, OK,
we can do the duplication.
I think we have methods that
are established to do that.
We can also do
language filtering.
But then if you want to filter
the data to remove garbage
and lower quality files, how do
you come up with good filters?
You can for sure find some
filters in the literature,
but if you want to really
build a data set that
is better than what
exists, you need
to invest some time trying
to find more techniques
that work better for your case.
This can be done with manual
inspection, which is always
a good idea to look at the
data and see what it actually
looks like.
And you can come up with filters
to help you during the training.
But that is usually
not enough because you
might have an intuition for
a filtering that works better
for your model.
But then when you train,
actually, this filtering
doesn't help.
And for example, for us, when
we were developing the StarCoder
series of models, we
were thinking, OK,
what are the best ways
for us to filter code?
So we use some standard
filters, for example,
to remove auto
generated content,
but we try to come
up with a little bit
more complex filtering
that could help us.
Looking for files that
have a lot of comments
because code that is
usually well documented
is probably of a higher quality
than another code file that
doesn't have any comments.
So we implemented
this filter that
looks for files that
have almost no comments,
and then removes them.
And we train the model
on that and turned out
the performance improvement
was really negligible.
It was not as much
as we thought.
We also tried to use
another filter, which
is using the stars
of a repository
as an indicator of quality.
So we tried removing all
the files from repository
that have less than five stars,
and this ended up removing over
70% of the data sets.
And then when we
trained on it, the model
was the worst model that we
trained in all our ablation
experiments, simply because
it removed too much data.
It was not worth using
this filtering technique.
This is why it's very important
that when you have a filter,
you should run what we
call an ablation model.
The ablation is basically,
you take a subset of your data
set after you
applied the filtering
and you train a
small model on it
and see how it behaves with
and without the filtering.
And you might be wondering,
OK, if I use a small model,
but does it really
extrapolate to larger models?
I think that's a good question.
But generally, from
our experience,
we found that this
does extrapolate
for most of data ablations.
When you're doing
these ablations,
you should select a set
of high signal benchmarks
that could give you
some conclusions
about the effect of your
filter early in the training.
This can be some of the popular
NLP benchmarks for LLMs.
For example, HellaSwag or MMLU.
And you should also--
sorry, here it's not tran,
it's train with different seeds
to reduce the noise
because sometimes you
can have filtering techniques
that don't give you
a very big difference.
But if you train with just one
seed, you must draw conclusions
but they're actually just noise.
So if you can and
you have the compute,
it's always better to run
the same experiment with two
or three different
seeds, and then
maybe do something
like the averaging
so that you reduce
the noise and you
have more robust conclusions
about the effects
of your filtering.
For example, for the
fine web data set,
the authors run over
200 plus ablations.
These were 1 billion
models trained on, I think,
30 billion tokens.
And this is how they were able
to find filterings that worked
better for their data sets.
Now let's go back to
our StarCoder use case
and I will tell you about how
we filtered the stack data sets.
So for the version
one, if you remember,
we had 6 terabytes
of source code.
But when we trained
StarCoder, we only
used 800 gigabytes
of these 6 terabytes.
So a lot of this data was
filtered out after our filtering
or curation.
The same happened for the
stack V2, where this time we
started from 32 in 600
programming languages,
and after the
filtering we ended up
with only 6.3 terabytes of code.
And for filtering
code, the approach
is a bit similar to
just filtering web data,
but the filtering techniques
are a bit different.
So first, we wanted to include
a lot of programming languages
and we looked at them and
we didn't keep all of them.
We only kept the popular
ones and excluded,
for example, configs
and languages that
are no longer maintained,
so this was what V1.
For StarCoder 2, we included
more languages over 600,
and then we added
some other sources
that could be interesting for
a code model to learn from,
which are GitHub issues, Git
commits, and Jupyter Notebooks.
We also added for the v2,
Kaggle, notebooks, and pull
requests.
Our second step
after we selected
the languages we wanted to train
on was data quality inspection.
So basically, as
I told you, we had
some filters to remove
low quality files
and autogenerated content.
An example is the
average line length.
So if we have an average
line length that is too high,
there's probably something
wrong with this file
or it's probably auto generated.
But since we had almost
100 programming languages,
we should not use
the same threshold
for all the languages
for this filter
because some programming
languages just
have longer lines.
So it's important to
do some inspection
and look at some samples
from these languages.
In our case, we had
the BigCode community
which helps us look at
100 samples per extension
and derive the appropriate
thresholds and filtering
heuristics.
The third deduplicate--
sorry, filtering step
was near-deduplication.
We found that near-deduplication
was the filtering that gave us
the most performance boost.
It's also very easy to apply
because it's language agnostic.
Even though we have 86
programming languages,
we don't need to change the
duplication for each language.
We can just apply
it to the whole sub,
to the whole data set.
And here I show you some
results of the effects
of the duplication.
For example, here you can see
this model Python all licensed.
If the filtering is
done, you get a pass
at one, which is our
code metric of 13.
But if you apply no duplication,
you go from 13 to 17.
That's a very big
performance bump.
The same goes for other subsets
like permissive license.
So we decided to use
deduplication for our data set
and to use strong
deduplication to really remove
all the files that
could be similar.
Another step is
in our pipeline is
to remove personal
identifiable information.
So this could be names,
emails, or keys, or passwords
because we scraped
code from GitHub.
And although GitHub
has some tools
to detect secrets and
prompt users to remove them,
that's not always the case.
And we found that
there was still
a lot of secrets
in the data sets.
And we train a
model, you don't want
it to be trained on that because
in inference, it might generate
sensitive or personal data.
So our approach to removing it
was to first annotate the data
sets for PII.
We collaborated with
an annotation company
to annotate some samples.
So the annotators were
tasked with the labeling PII
when they found it.
For example, if they find the
name, they give it a class name.
If you find an email, they
also label it as an email.
So it was a named
entity recognition task.
And then we trained
the StarPII, which
is our NER model
to detect this PII,
and then we run it on the
whole StarCoder training data.
This took almost 800 GPU
hours because it's a more--
it's a neural network and
it needs to run on GPUs.
The last step in our filtering
was data decontamination
because you should make sure to
remove the benchmarks and test
sets from your training data.
Otherwise, your evaluation
numbers will just be inflated.
So we made sure to
remove the benchmarks
that we use for evaluation
from our training sets.
The last step in the data
curation of the stack
was to format the data.
So now that the data is
filtered and because code
is different from
text, we can allow
ourselves to apply some
nice formatting that
could help us during inference.
For example, for StarCoder,
we had the code file,
but before the code,
we added some tokens
that indicate that this
is the repository name
and another token file name
that indicates the file
name and another one for stars.
And this is interesting because
this model resembles StarCoder
and other code models.
I guess their main use case
is to be plugged in an IDE,
for example, VS Code.
And when you're
using them, it could
be interesting to
append the code
file with the name of
the file, for example,
I don't know, file.py
so that the model would
know this is the Python file.
If it's in another language,
when you add the file name
and you have the
extension, it could
know that this is detect
the language that it
should generate code in.
We also added GitHub stars
token and we try to play with it
to say, "This file
has the 100 stars."
And see if the model would
generate higher quality
code than if it were to
generate for zero stars.
We didn't find any differences
really during inference,
but it was fun to add
all this formatting.
For StarCoder2, one
of the improvements
was that StarCoder2
was repository aware.
Because when we have GitHub
repositories, it's repository.
So we have some files that are
in the same repository that
are related to each other.
But when we built
the stack V1, we just
shuffled files so
we kept-- we didn't
keep this repository structure.
And we trained the model,
we just shuffled them
and the model did not
know if two files belong
to the same repository.
But when we did
StarCoder2, we try
to keep files that are
in the same repository
next to each other.
And how we did that is
by concatenating them
with some special tokens like
file SEP, which basically
separates files.
And this way, the
model can know which
files need the same
repository and try
to find links between them.
3D parallelism, and then you
have also LightEval for doing
the evaluation.
So this is a stack to be able
to run your full trainings,
but also your ablation models.
You can apply a
filter from datatrove
and then train with nanotron
and evaluate with LightEval,
and they're well
integrated together
and they make one ecosystem.
So that's for general LLMs.
For code LLMs, we
also released the code
we used for both the stack
and StarCoder models,
and our BigCode
repository on GitHub.
And I think we just answered
our third question, which
was how to filter the data.
So now, you know how to--
first, how much data you need,
and then where you can get
this data, both web, and code,
and synthetic, and curated.
And you also know how you
can properly filter the data
and you can test the
filtering techniques
that you have in mind.
So now, let me tell you a
little bit more about code LLMs
because that's what
I'm working on.
And I'm trying to give you
a little bit of an overview
about these models so that you
know how to train good LLMs,
but you also know how to build
very cool code assistants
and completion models.
So how all of this
started was when
GitHub Copilot was released.
And it was very interesting
because it was so much better
than all the other code
completion models that
were before it, which were very
small and much less performance.
And GitHub Copilot was using
the Codex model by OpenAI.
And they just showed that
you can train or code LLM
in the same way that you train
an for English, for example.
You can just take a
large transformer model
and give it a lot of code data
and it will learn this code.
Because before, a
lot of people were
trying to treat code very
differently, for example,
by using abstract syntax trees.
But what Codex model
showed is that you
can treat code like text.
And if you want to
predict the next line,
you can predict the
next text, you just
do next token prediction
and you get your code.
It works very well, much better
compared to the more feature
engineering techniques.
And that was over two
years ago and we didn't
have any good open code models.
But today, if you go to the hub,
you can find that we have over
1,700 models that
are trained on code.
So these are models that
are either trained only
on code or LLMs that included
code as part of their training.
So you can see that we've
made a lot of progress
in this code generation
field, which is amazing.
And this is the word-- this is
the result of the committee's
work to build very good
instruction-tuned models
and base models.
For example, here, as you
can see in the leaderboard,
we have some very strong
models that score almost 80%
on the code evaluation
benchmark, which
is human eval, which
means they get almost 80%
of the problems right, which
is a very large number.
And when talking about the
landscape of open code LLMs,
in BigCode, we have
released the stack data set,
which is now the default
data set for training
on code, and also StarCoder1 and
StarCoder2 two family of models,
and other instruction-tuned
models with the H2 team
like StarChat2.
Meta also released some very
good code models which are
the code Llama series of
models that go from 7B to 70B.
There are also the deep C models
which are also very strong,
and they have also other models
like the recent Granite models
from IBM, CodeQwen,
CodeGen, and StableCode.
So there are different
providers for code LLMs
and also for data sets for code.
And the main reason we started
the BigCode collaboration
and to train our models was
to have a collaboration where
we have full data transparency.
We released all the
details about the training,
but also the data is
public so that people
can inspect it and use it.
And we also have the code for
the processing and the model
weights.
And the collaboration was open.
We had over 1,000 researchers
join our Slack and following
the journey with us.
And this created a
BigCode ecosystem
where the stack was
used in the pre-training
of a lot of
prominent code models
like CodeGen and StableCode.
And the StarCoder
models were used
as basis for a lot of
community fine tuning.
And I think it's
very important to be
aware of what makes
a release of an LLM,
whether it be a code
LLM or general LLM
open and responsible.
And I think this is four-fold.
First, it's really
good for the community
and for research
in AI in general.
If you can make open access
data sets, this will help.
This will mean having
data inspection tools,
but also opt out tools to
respect people's wishes
regarding their data sets.
For example, if they don't want
to be included in the trainings,
they should be able to opt out.
It's also important to
remove personal identifiable
information.
So an open release does not mean
just releasing model weights
and stopping there, but also
making your work reproducible
by fully documenting the
pipeline for using these models
and also releasing tools for
evaluation and technical reports
that documents the
whole pipeline.
And for us in BigCode,
we went from SantaCoder,
which was part of our
ablations to understand how
to filter the stack data sets.
And then we went to StarCoder
which was released last year,
a 15 billion code
generation model.
And then this year,
we released StarCoder2
which was trained on much
more programming languages
and had a much higher
evaluation score.
And StarCoder was also rated
as the most transparent model
by the Stanford Foundation
model transparency
index, which is really
heartwarming given
the efforts that we put
into data governance
and into making the
model release as
transparent as possible.
Regarding evaluation, so
for example, StarCoder 15B,
when it was released, it was
the state of the art code model.
And this was also the case for
StarCoder 215B among other 15B
models.
And it was even close or
better than larger models.
I think I don't have the plot
here, but it was better than--
it was matching code Llama 34B,
and it was close to DeepSeek 33B
on some benchmarks.
And here, for example,
you can see the results
on different benchmarks because
when releasing our model,
it's really important
that you don't just
evaluate on one benchmark,
but you should add
as many benchmarks as you want.
In case you had
contamination, although we
try to avoid this one benchmark,
there's a very low chance
that you also have contamination
on other benchmarks.
And it also allows you
to fully understand
how your model behaves if you
add more evaluation benchmarks.
And I think that's just a good
practice that everyone should
be doing with their releases.
So with the StarCoder models,
we also released some tooling
like VS Code implementation,
which also has a membership
test that tries to see
if the generated code was
in the training data and
highlight that to the author.
So that's part of
our code attribution
efforts for these code models.
Maybe you're interested in
using these models to build
your own personal
Copilot and fine tuning
StarCoder or Code Llama or other
models on your personal code
bases.
To do that, there's a very nice
blog post by Sourab and Sayak,
where they try to
take a code model
and train it on the Hugging
Face internal libraries,
and then deploy it in old Llama
and have a local code assistant.
And the pipeline is very similar
to what we did in pre-training.
First, you take
your data set, you
try to filter out the things
you don't want to keep,
and then you do deduplication,
and you train your model.
So in this case, it will
be just a fine tuning,
so it will be much quicker.
You can use libraries
like PEFT which
do parameter efficient fine
tuning where you don't need
to train all the
parameters of your models,
but you only inject few
trainable parameters.
This makes the
training much faster.
For example, 7B model can be
trained in a Google Colab.
Now, let's go back
to evaluation.
So, for example,
for LLMs, there's
the open LLM leaderboard
that evaluates models.
There's also the LLMs arena,
which compares instructs models
and uses human evaluation.
For code models, one of
the most popular benchmarks
is human eval.
And it's basically
a benchmark where
you have a function that the
model has to autocomplete.
And then when the
function is completed,
you take this solution and then
you run it against multiple unit
tests and you count
how many solutions pass
and how many solutions fail.
And then you count what we a
metric that we call pass at one.
For example, this
is the one that's
been reported in
this leaderboard
and this gives you
the human eval score.
There's also a translation
of this benchmark
to 18 other languages.
Here, I show Java and
JavaScript and C+ plus.
And this benchmark
is called MultiPL-E.
So it allows you to see
how well each model does
on which programming language
and choose the one that's
the most interesting for you.
But these benchmarks
usually have an issue
of contamination and
overfitting, especially
instruction-tuned models.
I don't know if you've already
checked what these data sets
look like, but
usually for code, they
are an instruction that asks the
model to generate an exercise.
And often, if you
look at them, they
look really similar
to human eval which
is function implementations.
So there's a very high chance
of having contamination,
which means having
some files that
look like human eval exercises
in your instruction tuning data
set.
So here, for example, this
plot is from the LiveCodeBench
leaderboard, and they find
that some benchmarks may
be overfitting on human eval.
And so their solution was
to have a leaderboard called
LiveCodeBench where
they regularly scrape
new problems from platforms like
code contests and leaked code.
And they evaluate
the models only
on the problems that were
released after the model release
date.
This way, they are sure that
there is no contamination.
And for example, that
was the case here.
They tried to evaluate these
models on all the data they
have, and then they can
compare the performance
to the data that was only
released after the model
release.
And they found that
some models were not
consistent in their results.
So that's one interesting
thing to keep in mind.
And this is also
another leader for this
will be interesting to compare
not just open models, but also
closed models like GPT-4 and
see where the open source
community is standing
compared to these code models.
So that was my presentation.
Thank you very much
for your attention.
And if you have any
questions, I can answer them.
Yes, thank you very much for
the great insightful talk.
So we have some
questions here on Slido.
So I'm not sure if there are
any in-person questions or else
I will get started with
the Slido question.
Sure.
OK, guess not.
So I'll ask some of
the questions online.
I think I had submitted
some of these as well.
It seems like there's some
questions about synthetic data.
Let me see.
I was also wondering about this.
So someone's asking what
are the consequences
of training AI models on
AI-generated synthetic data?
Do you foresee any
problems with this?
And there's a related question.
Does synthetic data
closely represent
the natural distribution
of language.
I assume some low
quality data from humans
is necessary for things
like learning robustness
and so forth.
Yeah, sure.
These are very great questions.
So about the consequences
of training models
on AI-generated data, I
can think of two main ones.
First is enforcing some
biases because models already
have some biases.
And if we train on data
that is generated by them,
we might be enforcing
it even more.
The other thing is, for
example, contamination.
These models might be trained--
might generate content that
looks like the evaluation
benchmarks.
And when you train on
that, you will have
contamination in your data.
So, for example, one of the
critiques of the five model
is that people, because they
did not see the synthetic data
and the models were very
good on the benchmarks,
they were very skeptical.
Are these models really good
or are they just overfitting
on the benchmarks?
So I think contamination
and enforcing
biases are one of the main
things to keep in mind.
And regarding synthetic
data not being
the same as a web
distribution, I
think that's a very good point.
And for example, when we
were developing Cosmopedia,
first, we found that it
was worse than the web,
and which was surprising because
we spent a lot of time trying
to curate this data
set which looks so much
cleaner than the web.
And then adding some
web data and trying
to add like more
topics was able to help
us compensate some of the gaps.
But adding some web always
gives you a performance boost.
So yes, there is some noise
and some specific patterns
in web data that
will probably need
to be included in
the training mix
to keep a whole coverage of
what's natural distributions
look like.
So it sounds like you're
saying a good training
set would have a
mix, potentially,
of synthetic and natural data.
Is that correct?
Yeah, I think so.
Some experiments were on show
that that's the case because you
can try to spend some time to
carefully curate the topics,
but you'll probably be
missing out on some things.
And the human
intuition that we have
is not always what works
for training models.
It seems that keeping
some filtered web helps.
And also, if you see the
technical reports, for example,
in [INAUDIBLE], they insist
a lot on filtering the web
and including it in
the pre-training.
And I think that now seems
like maybe the best way to go.
But that makes sense.
Great.
Another question is, is
RLHF type preference data
more important than
unsupervised pre-training data?
Should we spend more
resources on RLHF data?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So for example, the
unsupervised pre-training
is mainly to get base
models, but then you
can't use these base
models as chat assistants.
You need to do another step.
So you can either do
RLHF, but nowadays, people
are just doing
instruction tuning
without needing to go
through RL where you just
train the model on pairs of
instructions and solutions,
and that seems to
work very well.
And there are now
some methods that
don't use reinforcement learning
but work as well, for example,
DPO or ORPO.
So I think if you want
to chat assistant,
you definitely need to run
a supervised training on top
of the unsupervised one,
but it doesn't necessarily
have to be RLHF.
There are some other
algorithms now.
Great.
And here's a
multimodal question.
Does multimodal
grounding, for example,
including images and
videos along with the text,
reduce the need for so
much text-only data?
Yeah what do you mean?
I'm sorry.
Well, the question is asking,
does multimodal grounding
help, basically?
If you have images and
videos along with the text,
does this reduce the amount
of text-only data required
to train models?
So I can't probably answer
that because I haven't tried,
but I guess, all for example,
the multimodal models,
for example, that were
recently released,
there's always a
significant text portion.
That seems the case for
most vision language models.
But yeah, I don't know, really,
about the percentages for each.
Right, OK.
A more general question.
You probably touched
upon some of this,
but are there any
major differences
between training text
versus code models
other than the training
data being different?
Yes, that's a good question.
So the training
data is different.
Regarding the training itself,
we use a similar architecture.
For example, StarCoder, it was a
Llama or a Mixtral architecture.
I think one thing
that you probably
want is long context
because if you
want to use these models,
for example, in VS code,
then you want to add all
the neighboring files
in the context.
You should be able to
fit a very large context.
So we try to do some
long context extension.
But again, people
also do this for LLMs.
We also care a lot
about inference.
So we use first, MQA and then
GQA to have faster inference.
But these are also techniques
that are implemented for LLMs.
So I'd say overall,
it's very similar.
But yeah, maybe we should
prioritize some things
like having a smaller
model that can
be used for, for example,
IDE is faster than actually,
a much larger model that
would need more deployment.
Yeah.
All right, great.
Here's also a general question.
I guess they're
asking for advice.
So if you have a very
tiny compute budget,
for example, a single
GPU, what would you
recommend prioritizing?
Let's assume you're
fine tuning a model.
Yeah, so I think,
for example, now
there are some great solutions
for on-device deployment
and fine tuning.
For example, you can
run quantized models
with Llama CPP or
other frameworks.
And with the
techniques like PEFT,
you don't need to do full model
fine tuning and you should be
able to run this on one
GPU even in 7B model.
So I think you should just
find a very well curated data
sets because quality is more
important than quantity,
and then use one of these
techniques for easy fine tuning
and that should work.
All right, great.
Here's a question asking--
I guess, different
from pre-training,
but they're saying,
I'm guessing,
the optimal amount
of training data
depends heavily on the domain as
well as the task at hand, right?
Yes, probably.
Now, we're following the
Chinchilla scaling laws.
I think they tried to
compare English to code,
and they found that the
findings still hold.
But maybe if you go
to another domain,
I don't know, like medical,
things could change.
And that's why I mentioned
the DeepSeek paper
where they mentioned
that it's really
heavily dependent on data.
And for them, it
was the same domain.
They just changed data sets,
going from one generic data set
to another, well curated one,
and things started changing.
So I think that's
probably the case.
But it's underexplored
how these scaling laws
change depending on domains.
So it's good to be
aware of that when
developing models for domains
that are not explored by these--
Speaking of different
domains, code versus text,
someone is asking, what are some
of the interesting differences
between tokenizing for
general purpose text
versus for code generation?
Yeah, so when we were
training the tokenizer,
I think one thing that
was important to keep
was number splitting, and
we use the standard bpe.
And we were training it.
We trained on our data set that
we were using for this training
data, so our code mixture.
And we did some
analysis to see if there
are any outliers,
any tokens that
were underrepresented
or overrepresented
as sanity checks.
But overall, it's very
close to the text training.
And now, most LLMs have a
significant code portion
in their tokenizers so they're
also trained on a lot of code.
And at the end, you can use
either one tokenizer for LLMs
or for code or the other way.
Because even on code, you
have a lot of markdown,
so there's a lot of
English, so you end up
representing all the
English tokens, for example,
in your code tokenizer.
All right, great.
And here's a question
about fine tuning, I guess,
compared to pre-training.
So they're asking, do the same
principles apply for fine tuning
or would you make a different
or additional recommendation?
So yeah, for fine
tuning, I think
when you're preparing the data,
it's probably a different thing.
You're not going to train
on all of the stack.
You probably want to continue
training on specific language.
So maybe you could
invest more time
to even heavily filter
because for fine tuning,
you don't need as much
data as for pre-training.
For example, for
us, the filtering
we tried, for
example, stars didn't
work because they
removed a lot of data
and we did not have enough
for our pre-training.
Well, for fine tuning, for
example, for instruction tuning,
there was the Lima paper where
they instruction tuned only
on 1,000 instructions and they
had a model that was much better
than train on
millions of samples.
So I think that situation is
even much more important when
it comes to fine tuning.
Great.
One last question, I guess.
So you might have also
touched upon this briefly,
but what are some considerations
to make when publishing
very large data sets, and more
nuanced or less known things
to be aware of?
Yeah, so maybe on
the technical side,
releasing tools also for
filtering and documentation.
That's what we tried
to do with the stack.
And maybe more on
the governance side,
be aware of where the
licenses are respected, where
the copyright is respected.
Do you have an opt out
tool for your data sets?
And maybe try to
release it on the hub
to make it easily
accessible for people.
If there are some concerns,
you could try to add a gate.
For example, for us,
we release the data set
that we used for PII detection,
but we add some gating mechanism
because it was
sensitive information.
So it's good to think of
this things in advance
before releasing the data sets.
But yeah, in general,
these are my advice.
Great.
Do we have any
in-person questions?
If not, then we can
probably conclude.